# 哈喽 大家好
Hi everyone
# 最近我朋友从珠海给我寄了一盒这个血蛤
Recently my friend sent me this box of blood clams from Zhuhai
# 正好我伯爷没吃过了
My uncle has never tasted it before
# 然后今天就做一个什么呢
So today we shall cook a ...
# 白灼血蛤来吃吧
'Bai Zhuo Xue Ha' (blanched blood clam)
# 这个雪蛤就是我刚刚开了一个给我四伯看
This clam... I just opened one to show my uncle
# 这个里面真的会流血
That it truly 'bleeds'
# 所以叫做雪蛤
So it's called 'blood clam'
# 而且这个特别适合血压高的人吃
This clam is very suitable for those with hypertension
# 然后它寒性非常大
But it is very 'cold' (according to traditional Chinese medicine)
# 如果肠胃不好的人
If you don't have the strongest digestive system,
# 你尽量就不要吃这个
Please avoid eating this clam
# 这个营养好的很四伯爷
This clam is very nutritious, uncle
# 看那个样子都可以
It looks like so
# 我去弄点水来洗哈都
Let me get some water to wash them
# 把它倒进去洗一下
Pour them into the bowl and wash them
# 一起刷嘛
Let's brush them together
# 在这个血蛤在沿海地区
The blood clam... in coastal areas
# 有的朋友他喜欢吃生的
Some people prefer eating blood clams
# 但是我们四川这边还是比较难接受这个
But here in Sichuan, most people may not like raw clams
# 我四伯说生的他
My uncle says that raw food...
# 生的咋个吃嘛
Why would I eat raw clams?
# 就是啊
That's true
# 还有一个就是要肠胃够好
Another issue is that, you need to have a strong digestive system
# 肠胃不好的不可以吃
Otherwise, don't eat this
# 肠胃不好的吃了这个要
If your digestive system is not good enough, you'll...
# 要拉肚子是不
Have diarrhea?
# 嗯 肚子要遭
Yep. You'll have digestive problems
# 我伯爷说这个要多洗几下
My uncle says that this should be washed for more times
# 他说有一点点泥的话都不放心吃起来
He won't rest assured even if there's just a little bit mud left
# 看嘛 洗完水都是清亮（干净）的
See? The water after washing is still clear
# 我们这里可能有三四斤吧
We may have 3 to 4 Jin (~ 1.5-2 kg) of clams here
# 我们刷了差不多一个小时
We've been brushing them for almost an hour
# 这个如果你们要吃的话
If you also want to eat this
# 可以在海鲜市场买他们刷好的
You can buy brushed ones at the seafood market
# 不要像我这个因为是朋友送的嘛
Well since these are given by my friend
# 不可能叫他刷好了再给我送过来
I can't have him brush these for me
# 我再切一点这个姜跟葱
Let me cut some ginger and spring onion
# 然后再弄一点这个大蒜 还有辣椒
Some garlic and chili pepper as well
# 做一个蘸水
to make a dipping sauce
# 等下万一吃不惯这个纯味的
If we are not used to the 'original' blanched clams
# 我们就蘸一个川味的
We can enjoy them in Sichuan style
# 好了 这个就切好了
Ok. This is done
# 我们再切一点姜和葱
Let's cut some ginger and spring onion
# 就是在煮它的时候放进去
Add them into the wok while boiling the clams
# 真的这个东西吃的来的吃生的营养价值很好
For sure, the raw clams might be really good for your health
# 是
Yep
# 就是很多可能都吃不来
But they may not be acceptable to most people
# 我再放点酱油进去
Let me add some light soy sauce
# 诶呀 可以了
Ok. This is done!
# 走嘛 帮我端哈四伯爷
Let's go. Would you help me with this bowl?
# 这个时候咋个做
How do we cook it?
# 这个水开了放下去
When the water is boiling, put the clams into the wok
# 煮十多秒钟
Boil them for slightly more than 10 seconds
# 12秒钟就差不多
12 seconds might be ok
# 放入姜葱和水一起烧开
Add ginger and spring onion into the wok and boil them with the water
# 水开后放入血蛤
When the water is boiling, put the blood clams into the wok
# 12秒之后把血蛤捞出来
After 12 seconds, take the clams out of the water
# 这个打开里面还有血 看嘛这种最好吃
This one still has 'blood'. See? This type is the most delicious
# 嗯
Yep
# 嗯 很鲜
Hmm. Very tasty
# 我就是看到这肠肠多
I see a lot of intestines...
# 不不不 不弄肠子 直接吃四伯爷
No no no.. don't remove the intestines. Just eat the whole thing, uncle
# 好了 我们来尝一下这个
Ok. Let's try the dipping sauce
# 怎么样
How do you like it?
# 吃得惯不
Can you get used to it?
# 吃得惯
Yes
# 你蘸一哈这个辣的嘛 你如果吃起腥的话
Just dip the clam in the spicy sauce here, if you think it's too fishy
# 吃得来
I think it's ok
# 安
Huh?
# 吃得来
I think it's ok
# 吃得来是不
You like it?
# 嗯
Yep
# 来嘛尝哈这个蘸哈辣的怎么样
Come and try how it's like with this spicy dipping sauce
# 我试哈看嘛
Let me try
# 嗯
Wow
# 蘸哈辣的更辣 吃起更酸辣
It tastes spicier with this sauce. Sour and spicy
# 我们这个血蛤 有的人他吃这个血蛤
This blood clam... Some people like eating it...
# 这水开了之后放进去十秒钟捞出来
after just 10 seconds of boiling
# 要什么效果呢
They like the status where...
# 就是要这种没有张开 自己把它掰开的这种
the clams are not opened yet. You still need to open them
# 如果掰不开的话用硬币在后面拧一下就开了
If you can't open the clam with your hands, you can use a coin to open it from the back
# 这个打开了之后一定要见到有红色的液体
You should see the red liquid after opening
# 就是类似这种红色的
Just like this... the red liquid
# 这个水特别鲜
The 'juicy' is extremely tasty and umami
# 很多人吃不惯这个（生的）
Many people are not used to this (raw clam)
# 我还吃得来这个东西
Well, I'm ok with it
# 吃得来是不
You like it?
# 吃得来
Yup
# 先我还以为像鱼一样没去肠子这些
Previously I thought it's like a fish with intestines...
# 我还有点夹口 我还不敢吃
I thought it might taste weird so I was reluctant #夹口貌似是指食物中含碱过多或者没熟而口感不佳，使舌头感到发麻、干涩，这里就意译了
# 唉呀 我管三七二十一哦 我大到胆子吃2个看
Then I was like 'screw it! Just be bold and eat some'
# 哎 我吃起还好吃 安逸
Surprisingly this is very delicious. Nice!
# 是不
Isn't it?
# 是呀
Tasty indeed
# 这个适合很多人吃
The blood clam is suitable for many people
# 然后如果你肠胃比较寒的话
However if you have a relatively poor digestive system
# 劝你就不要吃这个
I would not recommend this to you
# 因为你吃了这个很容易拉肚子
Because you'll easily have diarrhea after eating them
# 这个是很有凉性嘎
It's pretty 'cold', right?
# 嗯
Yes
# 还有就是在女性生理期的时候不要吃这个
In addition, for females during periods, please don't eat this
# 再一个就是产后不要吃这个
Also, females who just give birth should avoid eating this
# 这个东西特别适合什么（人）呢
The blood clam is suitable for these populations...
# 适合老年人吃
Such as elderly people
# 然后适合孕妇
Pregnant woman
# 适合这个做完月子之后吃
As well as females after the 'postpartum confinement' #感觉这个表达本身是带有对'坐月子'的反对，虽然我也反对坐月子...如果中性一点的翻译方法可以用postpartum period
# 营养很丰富
As it contains rich nutrients
# 你整的啥子哦
What do we have here?
# 我没吃过哟
I've never had this before
# 血蛤
Blood clams
# 嗯
Hmm
# 这个名字还多好听
Interesting name
# 伯娘你吃不来的话就蘸哈这个海椒
Aunt, if you can't get used to it, you can dip it in the chili pepper sauce
# 好吃
Delicious!
# 我们吃这个的时候把肉吃下去
When eating this, we eat the meat first
# 我专门吃这种跑出来的
I'll specially pick the ones out of the shell
# 里面会有一点汤
There's a little bit 'juice' in the shell
# 这个汤特别的鲜
which is very tasty and umami
# 嗯 好吃
Hmm. Yummy!
# 你高血压多吃点
You have hypertension. Just eat more
# 高血脂 高胆固醇的人特别适合
The clam is very suitable for those with high blood fat and cholesterol levels
# 这样子啊
Alright
# 嗯
Yep
# 我们这个东西的话在四川没有
We don't have this in Sichuan province
# 因为它是在沿海地区才有的
Because it can only be harvested in coastal areas
# 所以你要吃的话
So if you would like to have a try
# 要么在网上订 要不就是托在海边的朋友
You can either order some on the internet, or ask your friends by the sea...
# 好吃真的好吃
Delicious. Indeed.
# 寄过来
... to mail some to you
# 好啦 大家可以不是海边的朋友可以尝试一下
Ok. I recommend everyone... who doesn't live by the sea to try this
# 下次你哥哥回来 我喊他从珠海带点回来
Next time when your cousin returns from Zhuhai, I'll ask him to bring some back #这里哥哥大概率指的是堂哥？
# 嗯
Okay
# 好
Ok
# 那边他肯定买得到撒
He can definitely buy some there, right?
# 买得到
Yes of course
# 好了 本期视频就到这里
Ok. That's the end of this video
# 我们要吃这个美味的海鲜
We are gonna enjoy the delicious seafood
# 血蛤
Blood clam
# 我还吃得来
I like it
# 好了
Ok
# 本期视频就到这里 拜拜
That's the end of this video. Bye-bye!
# 做拜拜撒你
Aunt: Say bye-bye
# 我还要吃啥子拜拜哦
I'm still eating. Why bye-bye?
# 我要吃舒服了才拜拜
I'll say bye-bye only after I'm done